My name is Jared Todd and I'm going to talk to you a little bit about the selection of the steel and why it's important in the style of knife that you choose.
Your steel that you choose needs to be able to become hard.
There's mild steel, which is usually ten eighteen, which means it only has .18 percent of carbon.
It doesn't have enough to get hard when you heat treat it, so it won't hold any type of an edge, which is most steel that you would find at hardware stores.
In order to get a good edge and retain that edge, you're going to need a knife that has at least half of a percent of carbon, up to one percent.
The steel that I choose to make most of my knives out of is what's called fifty-one sixty, I get it in just a long bar.
I cut it up to the length that I need.
It has .60 of a percent of carbon along with other type of alloying elements in it to be able to harden deeper.
It's a very shock resistant steel.
It's basically the same type of steel that you have in your car leaf springs.
It hardens very well.
It holds an edge very well and it's very durable.
There's many different types of steel out there, there's stainless steel.
Stainless steel is stainless because it has a lot of chromium in it.
The chromium that's in the steel, part of it is absorbed into the iron molecule itself, the other part of the chromium is floating around in, basically in solution and that's what causes a steel to become stainless.
Stainless steel does not mean that it is not going to rust, it means it's stain less, it's going to stain less than a high carbon steel.
Technically, stainless steel will not hold as good of an edge as a high carbon steel, but in certain applications, stainless steel is a must, in kitchen knives, knives that's going to be used extensively in water, salt water.
And then, there are certain types of steels that you can select for those type of applications that will be able to hold a decent edge, but they're usually quite expensive.
Where a decent high carbon steel you can get for a couple dollars a pound, where a good stainless steel you're going to pay anywhere from fifteen to thirty dollars a pound in selecting the type of steel that you need.